[SPEAKER_03]: So, I've been thinking about, you know, yeah, Brahmaviharas, Brahmaviharas, what are they?
[SPEAKER_03]: And, so I've got so many ideas about it, so I just want to see what others think, you know.
[SPEAKER_03]: There's a few suttas that come to mind.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, on one occasion, a Brahmin went to the Buddha and said to him, it's astounding and amazing, Master Gautama, Master Gautama's faculties are tranquil and the color of his skin is pure and bright.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, whatever high or luxurious sitting place or beds there are, whatever grand elegant furnishings there are,
[SPEAKER_03]: Master Gautama surely gains them at will, without trouble or difficulty.
[SPEAKER_03]: In a way, he might be saying, you probably live in luxury, which is why you look so good.
[SPEAKER_03]: You probably, you know, things are going well for you, you're quite rich.
[SPEAKER_03]: And then he, the Buddha replies, those high and luxurious kinds of bedding or furnishings are rarely obtained by those who have gone forth.
[SPEAKER_03]: And if they are obtained, they are not allowed.
[SPEAKER_03]: But, Brahman, there are these three kinds of luxurious furnishings that I, at present, I gain at will, without trouble or difficulty.
[SPEAKER_03]: The celestial luxury, the divine luxury, and the noble luxury bedding, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, and it just goes, it says, the celestial
[SPEAKER_03]: The luxurious bed is the jhānas.
[SPEAKER_03]: That is how he travels.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's where he rests.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's his couch, how he abides.
[SPEAKER_03]: And then, the divine, high, luxurious bed is the brahmaviharas.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's how he travels.
[SPEAKER_03]: Whatever he's doing, he's just abiding in that.
[SPEAKER_03]: And then, the noble high luxurious bed is having been rid of any delusion, having been able to get rid of the taints and so on.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, he's abandoned, through the abandoning of sensuality, through the abandoning of your will, through the abandoning of ignorance, he abides in these three different vehicles, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, what I've come across, I'm sure everyone has come across this thing, this advice, that you can sometimes hear someone say, I get angry a lot with this person, or that, or whatever.
[SPEAKER_03]: What should I do?
[SPEAKER_03]: What... what's the... how do I go... how do I stop getting so angry?
[SPEAKER_03]: And the advice you hear is, well, just practice metta.
[SPEAKER_03]: Just do that.
[SPEAKER_03]: And it's like, well, just... just do the celestial... the celestial driving.
[SPEAKER_03]: Just do it.
[SPEAKER_03]: You know, how do you... how do I stop, you know, acting sensually?
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, just do jhāna.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, just do the jhāna.
[SPEAKER_03]: Just set it easy.
[SPEAKER_03]: Then you won't choose sensuality anymore.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, it's all just be... do metta and then you won't get angry anymore.
[SPEAKER_03]: But it is exactly the opposite way around.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's abandoning of the sensuality.
[SPEAKER_02]: A bannering of anger is how you do metta.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's how you would be able to get it.
[SPEAKER_03]: You cannot...
[SPEAKER_03]: There's two kind of practices.
[SPEAKER_03]: There's someone who's who's actually working towards jhāna, working towards the Ganga Mahārāja.
[SPEAKER_03]: And someone who has attained that, who has actually got that fruit, and now can use it to travel and to live his life.
[SPEAKER_03]: Fair.
[SPEAKER_03]: Fair, isn't it?
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, to vihāra, abide in it, and charity, yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: And look, but you cannot, you cannot use matter, you cannot pervade the world with matter.
[SPEAKER_03]: As long as anger is still arising.
[SPEAKER_03]: If you haven't generated it, you haven't grown it, you haven't developed it, you cannot cultivate it if you haven't developed it.
[SPEAKER_03]: How do you develop it?
[SPEAKER_03]: You don't just... you don't just... so how you develop is...
[SPEAKER_03]: So, for example, if we... so, speaking about metta, brahmavihāras, there's another sutta that says, where someone is saying, I...
[SPEAKER_03]: I do metta, brahmavihāras, but on occasion, you know, I do get angry.
[SPEAKER_03]: And the monks say, well, don't say that.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's wrong.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's impossible.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because if you have that,
[SPEAKER_03]: Because that is the fruit of abandoning ill-will.
[SPEAKER_03]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's the definition of matter.
[SPEAKER_02]: To have matter means you have abandoned ill-will already.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, if you say, I have matter, but ill-will still arises, means you haven't abandoned it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Thus, you don't have matter.
[SPEAKER_02]: And same with jhāna.
[SPEAKER_02]: Exactly same with jhāna.
[SPEAKER_02]: To have sensual thoughts arise, but have jhāna in the meantime, every now and then, that's also not possible.
[SPEAKER_02]: You're either abiding in jhāna, because you abandon the sensuality,
[SPEAKER_03]: But, so, it is quite common.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, I do jhāna, satya, I can abandon sensuality.
[SPEAKER_03]: Exactly, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: No, I'm not free from sensuality, but I also believe I'm doing jhāna, not being free from sensuality, it means jhāna.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, that is... also, again, I think this is... you can either just not do ill will,
[SPEAKER_03]: If anyone would understand that, I would say, do non-ill-will.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, there's ill-will, you're discerning it.
[SPEAKER_03]: That may be the intention of the mind to go in that direction, and you just non-it.
[SPEAKER_03]: You don't do it.
[SPEAKER_03]: But that requires a certain level, you know, you need to see your mind.
[SPEAKER_03]: You need to be able to see your mind.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, I think, eventually,
[SPEAKER_02]: Virtues of ill-will or non-ill-will can become apparent, but that's not the starting point.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, yeah, virtues, sense of strength and so on, seeing the mind and then having...
[SPEAKER_04]: But, practically, in, like, specifically in regard to this, it would be, you know, so, for example, like, if you... whatever would be physically done on account of ill-will, don't do it.
[SPEAKER_04]: Whatever would be spoken on account of ill-will, don't do it.
[SPEAKER_04]: Then, you know, whatever
[SPEAKER_04]: You, if you want to think about some something that's out of your will, don't do it.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then that's when the choice... And then what's left is, you realize, oh, I can now not do this.
[SPEAKER_02]: I can drop this, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_02]: But not before these three modes of expression of your will have been thoroughly developed.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you don't do anything by body, you don't do anything, you don't say anything verbally.
[SPEAKER_02]: Then, you go back to your solitude on your own, and the mind revolves around you full of ill-will, and you recognize, yeah, so there is mind of ill-will.
[SPEAKER_02]: As we said in the just previous talk, these thoughts are the indications of the state of mind.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, I should not fuel them, but I should not try to get rid of them either, because they're not the problem.
[SPEAKER_02]: I should see that the mind is still mind of ill-will that wants to go in the direction of these thoughts.
[SPEAKER_02]: Same with sensuality.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, I'll remain not allowing it.
[SPEAKER_02]: I will remain basically watching, watchful of this mind that wants to make me distracted so that it continues this momentum.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's all you need to do.
[SPEAKER_02]: For how long?
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, for as long as that mind pressures you to go in there, to willingly, as, you know, accept, delight, welcome the thoughts that are presented to you.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because by welcoming them, you stop seeing the mind.
[SPEAKER_02]: You fall from seeing it, and now you're immersed in thoughts.
[SPEAKER_02]: So that's how you would... Of course, that's the subtlest practice, but it can be done.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's nothing like, oh, how can this be achieved?
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you will still have the pressure of ill-will, you will still have occasional thought coming up about it, but you're not taking it up.
[SPEAKER_02]: And you're certainly not trying to paste over meta and, no, but he's a good person or something like that.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because none of that's the point.
[SPEAKER_02]: The point is, mind is affected with ill-will and it's tormenting you and I can't do it.
[SPEAKER_02]: And you're trying to fix things that are the result of the problem, not the problem.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, that's the gateway.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's the gateway, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: If you had sufficiently then protected that gateway, not welcome, not denied, not went overly too far out, not trying to run too far in either, then, exactly, you realize that the state of the mind of your will, it's like, okay, I don't care.
[SPEAKER_02]: Not my problem.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then these thoughts won't even come.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because now you have actually taken the mind.
[SPEAKER_02]: Now you can tell it what to do.
[SPEAKER_02]: No, drop that.
[SPEAKER_02]: Stop it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Before that, you couldn't tell it.
[SPEAKER_02]: You just had to protect everything they wanted... the mind wanted to take up and prevent the mind from taking it up.
[SPEAKER_00]: Could you say... when you said you don't allow the mind... Could you say one way of describing that could be to not become absorbed in the content?
[SPEAKER_00]: So...
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's how you don't allow.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: So you can't... you can't... as I said, for as long as you're still tormented by the content of your thoughts,
[SPEAKER_02]: You're not seeing your mind to the extent necessary for this choice, for this command to work.
[SPEAKER_02]: The mind is not pliable, as the Suttas would say.
[SPEAKER_02]: Not yet.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, the way to make it pliable is not to...
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay, mind, stop it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Learn how to talk to it.
[SPEAKER_02]: No, no, it's to...
[SPEAKER_02]: Overcome any tendency to move on account of thoughts that are there besetting you.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, don't welcome them, don't delight, don't open the door, don't go out trying to chase them, and certainly don't let them in.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's just ill will.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Ill will is there.
[SPEAKER_02]: It persists one way or the other, but your responsibility is on the level of welcoming, delighting, picking up all these thoughts.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, when that's sufficiently endured, for as long as it takes, then you are discerning now the state of the mind behind it.
[SPEAKER_02]: And, eh... sooner or later, that will result in, obviously, greater familiarity with the phenomenon of your own citta, there at the back, the mood, whatever it is.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then you can... Actually, no.
[SPEAKER_02]: No.
[SPEAKER_02]: Drop that.
[SPEAKER_02]: I won't get angry now.
[SPEAKER_02]: And the mind just drops it.
[SPEAKER_02]: And, oh, isn't it wonderful?
[SPEAKER_02]: Now it listens to me.
[SPEAKER_02]: You might be even surprised, first time it happens.
[SPEAKER_02]: You can't just be saying it to your mind like a mantra and somehow magically it will pick up.
[SPEAKER_02]: No, no, no, no, no.
[SPEAKER_02]: You got to do it rightly and when the time is right, when these things are not being
[SPEAKER_02]: When you are not distracted by these things, you're not... you're not trying to get rid of the thoughts or welcome them and so on.
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, now is the right time.
[SPEAKER_02]: Now you recognize the mind is pliable.
[SPEAKER_02]: Let me now direct it away from this unwholesomeness.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's pretty much when you start boarding the vehicle of metta and so on.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because the anger cannot or cannot enter you anymore.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because how it enters you?
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, it enters you through thoughts, enters you through body, through actions by body, by speech, by mind.
[SPEAKER_02]: Now those have been purified.
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, look, now you are in control of this vehicle that you can take it away from any direction of ill will.
[SPEAKER_02]: Or jhāna, take it away from any direction of hindrances and sensuality.
[SPEAKER_04]: I wonder could we, for example, like a very
[SPEAKER_04]: Broadly speaking, practical, like, a thought of ill-will is always, to some extent, on the level of so-and-so did something bad to me, or just did something bad.
[SPEAKER_04]: And then, usually, if you have this kind of view of
[SPEAKER_04]: Or even just generally, actually, if you say, I don't know, I shouldn't be angry with that person, the natural thing... That's the thing.
[SPEAKER_02]: The thought of ill-will, you realize, yeah, so I don't need to get rid of that.
[SPEAKER_02]: Just behind the thought of ill-will is an angry mind.
[SPEAKER_02]: And if you develop it, you tell that mind at the back to drop it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Not the thought.
[SPEAKER_02]: You don't deal with the thought.
[SPEAKER_02]: And if the mind drops it, the thought of ill-will, it's not the ill-will anymore.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's just the thought of, factually, somebody did something.
[SPEAKER_02]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: But there is no ill-will in its core.
[SPEAKER_04]: That's what I was getting at.
[SPEAKER_04]: Because, you know, a lot of the time then, you'd find yourself people trying to, sort of, like, reconstitute what somebody did.
[SPEAKER_04]: As good.
[SPEAKER_00]: As, oh, it wasn't that bad, or I understand.
[SPEAKER_04]: And that's all totally, kind of,
[SPEAKER_02]: Because it all results in you over overlooking where the mind is, where the problem is, and you want to deal with the thought, explain the thought, get rid of the thought, but it's like... that's not... that's not the point.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's the state of mind at the back.
[SPEAKER_02]: And even sometimes, if that mind doesn't listen to you, like, that sutra says, oh, he crushes his mind with the mind.
[SPEAKER_02]: People often tend that to mean, oh, I stop thinking.
[SPEAKER_02]: See, it's a... No.
[SPEAKER_02]: You crush the mind with the mind, which means, if you still think it's about the thoughts, you're not even seeing that mind, how can you crush it?
[SPEAKER_02]: Context.
[SPEAKER_02]: How can you stand your ground against it, when you're not even seeing it?
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it's the ultimate content, the ultimate peripheral.
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, that's where the mind is.
[SPEAKER_02]: And, yeah, crush that.
[SPEAKER_02]: Leave these thoughts.
[SPEAKER_02]: Irrelevant.
[SPEAKER_02]: Just overpower that mind over there, and nothing can bother you on a specific level.
[SPEAKER_02]: I mean, it's like, you develop that practice, you'll be an island.
[SPEAKER_02]: The master of thought.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it's not just some sort of management technique.
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, it's this, I think that.
[SPEAKER_02]: When it's this, it's this.
[SPEAKER_02]: When it's that, I stand up and it's like, yeah, good luck with that.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's very, I mean,
[SPEAKER_04]: It's very relevant, or it's not...
[SPEAKER_04]: It's relevant to the problem of suffering and freedom from suffering, obviously, but specifically also because, you know, when there's ill-will, so-and-so did something bad, naturally, the kind of the view of anger or ill-will is, I'm suffering because of what this person did.
[SPEAKER_04]: But it's like, if you see genuinely that the only reason you're suffering is actually because of the ill-will, the ill-will is the suffering of it, then there's literally no reason to... there's no basis for ill-will anymore, because there's, you know, what this other person did...
[SPEAKER_04]: So, what do you need to do then?
[SPEAKER_04]: ...is irrelevant.
[SPEAKER_02]: You realize you need to refrain.
[SPEAKER_02]: From jumping back into making it personal, when you know it's not about it, you know it's the presence of your will that's bothering, but still let me just...
[SPEAKER_02]: So it's like, oh, so lack of restraint is why the real will proliferates, not because of who said what and because of what you didn't say in return and so on.
[SPEAKER_02]: All that's irrelevant.
[SPEAKER_01]: Vāsaṃsuddhas do in fact state that by developing metta, for example, ill-will can be abandoned.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the context there is a noble disciple who already has right view, who already, through what we just described, knows what metta is and is uprooting the fetter of ill-will.
[SPEAKER_01]: The possibility that that is ever going to arise in the future.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that gets then mistaken for the idea, oh, the metta is instantly available, regardless of whether I now have ill-will.
[SPEAKER_01]: I can apply that as an antidote to the ill-will, but it's overlooked that that's dealing with a fetter.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's a somewhat different context.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: And also, as we just said, abandoning of ill-will
[SPEAKER_02]: Here's what the practice of metta is.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, develop metta to abandon ill-will.
[SPEAKER_02]: Abandoning of ill-will to not have ill-will.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's what it is.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it's not another positive thing you do in regard... in response to the ill-will.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, if there is still possibility of mind going back into the ill-will, develop metta further.
[SPEAKER_02]: Develop the non-ill-will further.
[SPEAKER_02]: Same with centrality, yeah?
[SPEAKER_02]: That's why the first jhāna is necessary for an anāgāmī or an arahant, i.e.
[SPEAKER_02]: the noble disciple, an arahant who are free from sensual desires.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's necessary in a sense of, by abandoning sensuality, by seeing the danger, the peril withdrawing from it, that's your jhāna.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, cultivate that experience that's free from sensuality long enough,
[SPEAKER_02]: And possibility for returning back to it will disappear.
[SPEAKER_02]: And equally possibility for taking things personally and turning it back into... misconceiving it will also disappear.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's what we're describing.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yes, the dwelling in jhāna is blameless, it's pure, it's... it's to be developed.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then I tell monk, okay, monk, now regard that
[SPEAKER_02]: Pure state of jhāna, blamelessness, when you walk, go to toilet, whatever else, regard that as the peril, the death, the dark, subject to impermanence, your suffering and all of that, and the mind will completely...
[SPEAKER_02]: So, when the mind turns away, doesn't want anything to do with the purified experience of jhāna, how can it possibly conceive returning back to, like, stuff that's
[SPEAKER_02]: Thousand times coarser and worse, such as sensuality and all the... that becomes inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's how the mind's free.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yes, it's somewhat the same towards the Brahman you harness.
[SPEAKER_03]: Exactly the same.
[SPEAKER_03]: This, yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: The phrase that you often read in suttas is, eh...
[SPEAKER_03]: live regarding one direction with the mind endowed with metta likewise the second the third the fourth direction thus above below across and everywhere and to all as to myself i live regarding the entire world with the mind endowed with meta vast exalted unobstructed without hostility without in will but you can only do that
[SPEAKER_03]: When you have, when you are without hostility, without evil.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, so one, one who has the matter then, then can start doing this.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, make it a vehicle of practice, yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: And regard the world, you know, so in all directions with that, that mind that's unobstructed.
[SPEAKER_02]: How do you, how do you lose that, that state of mind?
[SPEAKER_02]: Can it be, can it happen accidentally?
[SPEAKER_03]: No, you have to,
[SPEAKER_02]: You know, but every next thing it's gone.
[SPEAKER_02]: Impossible.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you lose it, but become careless.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, I lose it through my own actions.
[SPEAKER_02]: They take me away from it.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you need to protect it from yourself.
[SPEAKER_02]: From your own underlying tendencies.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, I'll just read another sutta, the Metta Sutta, and this is basically instructions for protection of that mind.
[SPEAKER_03]: And it begins with, this is what should be done by one by those who are skilled in goodness and fully understand the path of peace.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Skilled in goodness means knowing wholesomeness, wholesomeness, unwholesomeness, unwholesomeness.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, the path is at least...
[SPEAKER_02]: So, by those who have the right view.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, what do you do?
[SPEAKER_03]: This is what you do to protect that.
[SPEAKER_03]: They are capable, upright, or very upright.
[SPEAKER_03]: Good speech, gentle, not prideful, content, easy to support, unbusied with the duties, frugal in their habits, peaceful faculties, clever, not intrusive or greedy amongst families, not doing the slightest thing that the wise would find fault with.
[SPEAKER_03]: I'll just skip the middle of this sutta.
[SPEAKER_03]: Not acting against nor despising anyone anywhere, even when irritated by the perception of patīgā, resistance, not wishing suffering on anyone.
[SPEAKER_03]: Even as a mother would protect her only beneficial child, so too should all beings cultivate the unobstructed mind.
[SPEAKER_03]: With metta towards the entire world, cultivate an unobstructed mind, above, below, all around, unconfined, friendly and without enemies, whether standing, walking, sitting or lying down, not becoming wary, always remembering this, for this is the way of the gods.
[SPEAKER_03]: Attained to view, accomplished in insight and virtue, freed from the expelling of sensual desire, they never again are conceived in the womb.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, the part I left out, it's a kind of...
[SPEAKER_03]: I just find it a strange part, the middle part.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's kind of a thought and it goes, happy and secure, may all beings be happy.
[SPEAKER_03]: Whatever living beings they are, whatever they are, may all beings be happy.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, it's a kind of a...
[SPEAKER_03]: In a way, this is like
[SPEAKER_03]: Everything else is not... whatever.
[SPEAKER_03]: But take this and just repeat that mantra.
[SPEAKER_03]: May all beings be well.
[SPEAKER_03]: May your mother be well.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, kind of leave it out.
[SPEAKER_03]: But, yeah, that is...
[SPEAKER_03]: I'm not saying it's invalid, but...
[SPEAKER_03]: It's the only way to practice it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's the fruit, again.
[SPEAKER_04]: This is kind of funny, actually.
[SPEAKER_04]: I mean, because... because really...
[SPEAKER_04]: At least, yeah, because I think what you kind of recognize is, like, whether I wish it or not, I can't...
[SPEAKER_04]: I can't make other beings be well, and that's not the point.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's just not to... like, not... that's not where, yeah, where anger is.
[SPEAKER_03]: If you are doing... you're not acting out of anger, well, other beings, in that sense, are going to be well.
[SPEAKER_03]: You're not going to be causing an issue.
[SPEAKER_02]: If you're protecting their mind, you can't even act out of anger.
[SPEAKER_02]: You can't even act out of... speak out of anger, and so on.
[SPEAKER_02]: You wouldn't be revolving around the thoughts of anger either.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it's like, yeah, that's the greatest protection you can give to others.
[SPEAKER_02]: No will, no agitation, not taking it personally.
[SPEAKER_03]: Not irritated by the perception of resistance of any kind.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that's what...
[SPEAKER_02]: Agreeable, disagreeable, does not irritate you.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that's like the whole, the core of Brahma Vihāra practices, you know.
[SPEAKER_03]: The practice of non-resistance, non-ill-will, and just refining and refining and refining.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, non-ill-will, non... Because that's the upekkhā, isn't it?
[SPEAKER_02]: Upekkhā is the ultimate abandoning of patīgā.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: The slightest traces of patīgā.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, it's your complete non-resistance or craving, in that sense, towards pain.
[SPEAKER_03]: Where does pain arise?
[SPEAKER_03]: Where does resistance arise?
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, here.
[SPEAKER_03]: You're fundamentally resisting
[SPEAKER_03]: This body, the discomfort of it.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, in a way, you would... that's where you can start.
[SPEAKER_03]: That non-resistance to this being here, which is giving you some sort of pressure, some kind of irritation.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: Giving you, you know, that's your kind of... your
[SPEAKER_03]: The first being, the first living being, which you have your will towards, you know, that's the first port of call for your ill-will, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: The self-loathing.
[SPEAKER_03]: And if you self-loathe and hate or have ill-will towards this in-your-face discomfort that's right here, then, for sure, you're going to be the next out there.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's guaranteed.
[SPEAKER_02]: If somebody were to say, while we're at it, um, I don't self-loathe, I'm completely free from self-loathing, uh, but they still have sensual desires and they go towards insanity, would that be a valid statement?
[SPEAKER_02]: That would be impossible, exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: The only reason, exactly, you're still attracted to sense pleasures is because you're avoiding the discomfort, the patiga, the resistance of this.
[SPEAKER_02]: These senses unsatisfied, seemingly.
[SPEAKER_02]: I mean, I say seemingly because unsatisfied sense is real as such.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's only unsatisfied from your projection, projecting your satisfaction in and of itself.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's fine for what it is.
[SPEAKER_02]: It does not require a scratch.
[SPEAKER_02]: You imply a scratch.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's just an image, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, for as long as somebody is still attracted to sensuality, to that extent, they still resist this body.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, that's a cool thing, yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, if you can...
[SPEAKER_02]: So, start there.
[SPEAKER_02]: You won't be uprooting any other ill will externally, if you're not uprooting the patika internally.
[SPEAKER_02]: And you will know you're uprooting internally, if you're abandoning desires towards sense pleasures.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's exactly why Śrī Caitanya will abandon hand-in-hand.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, in a way, if someone was interested in practicing caring, proper caring for all beings, myself and everyone in the world, if that was your inclination, you could, you know, well, again, I want to develop great compassion and care for everything.
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, then, you shouldn't, you need to know what's unbeneficial, what's beneficial, be clear on that, and then start to
[SPEAKER_03]: Do what is beneficial for this being here first.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because if you don't sort this one out, where you've got no perspective, you can't help anyone else.
[SPEAKER_03]: If you're hurting the one that's closest to you, well, you might be helping that other being over there to some degree, but still your mind is
[SPEAKER_03]: It's a obstructed mind already.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's narrowed and on the basis of your ill will towards this.
[SPEAKER_03]: I don't care about myself.
[SPEAKER_03]: I care about all other beings.
[SPEAKER_03]: Okay, but that's the basis.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's hatred still.
[SPEAKER_03]: Your care for all others is based upon... A resistance to what's here.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, it's not obstructed.
[SPEAKER_03]: You're narrow-minded, basically.
[SPEAKER_03]: You have no perspective on what is good for others.
[SPEAKER_03]: In a way, you know, Steve, this being here as a... your child that you would look after, someone dear to you, that you would... okay.
[SPEAKER_02]: Somebody that needs help in a way that they don't necessarily know it, they don't know what's good for them, but you know what's good for them.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's already you.
[SPEAKER_03]: And it was quite relevant because if this person is agitated and upset and going through loads of pain, well,
[SPEAKER_03]: You're feeling it.
[SPEAKER_03]: You're the one feeling it.
[SPEAKER_03]: You're the one experiencing it.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, it's relevant.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, that's the whole, like, the thing of suitable, unsuitable food for the wound or for the animal, depending on the simile.
[SPEAKER_02]: But the point is, it's like, yeah, this creature here, this individual,
[SPEAKER_02]: I don't need to know why he likes this, why he doesn't like that, why his mind responds like this, when it's that.
[SPEAKER_02]: I need to just recognize that it is so.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, but I need to...
[SPEAKER_02]: I do need to know why.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's not my problem why this horse has such a preference, why this animal likes that.
[SPEAKER_02]: My problem is that I'm paired with it.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, if it's agitated, I'll have to suffer.
[SPEAKER_02]: If it's gripped by feverish lust, I have to suffer the consequences.
[SPEAKER_02]: If it's distracted, it's on me again.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, that's when you recognize that space between you and your own mind, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_02]: When you see it as a creature that needs taming, that does not necessarily know what's best for it.
[SPEAKER_02]: But you don't need to even figure out why is that so.
[SPEAKER_02]: All you need to do is stick to the fact that, well, if it's agitated, I'll pay the price.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, that's all I care about.
[SPEAKER_02]: I'll keep it calm, so it doesn't bother me.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's the point of view, recognition.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, if you have no ill will towards this creature,
[SPEAKER_02]: And you will have no ill-will towards this creature, you will have no resistance towards this creature.
[SPEAKER_02]: If you have started taming it and withdrawing it from the expressions of ill-will and patīgā, which are sensuality, expressions of sensuality, then, you can actually protect it rightly, you can have a context, and you don't need to teach it or explain to it what's happening.
[SPEAKER_02]: You just need to direct it away from the unsuitable pastures and keep it in the suitable ones.
[SPEAKER_02]: And it will start to listen to you, because then, eventually, even that creature will awake to itself and recognize, oh, yeah, no, this is actually what I always wanted.
[SPEAKER_02]: Thank you, by the way.
[SPEAKER_02]: I, you know, I could not see it, but you took me away from the unwholesome stuff, and now things are clear.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, centrality was always a boil, a pain, a charcoal pit.
[SPEAKER_02]: It was torture, but I didn't know that.
[SPEAKER_02]: Thank you for keeping me away now.
[SPEAKER_02]: I know it."
[SPEAKER_02]: And then you can let go of it, because it won't go back there, because it was truly not pleasant even back then.
[SPEAKER_02]: But it doesn't know.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's that whole kind of discrepancy that people would feel inside.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, but I know that it's unpleasant, but I can't help it.
[SPEAKER_02]: See, the problem is that they are identified with the mind.
[SPEAKER_02]: They don't see the mind, so they automatically took possession, took the point of view, so they think they want it.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, on one end, they know that it's not suitable and that it's resulting always... always resulting in pain.
[SPEAKER_02]: But then, when the pressure comes, they cannot not identify with the pressure.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, I want it and then they go back to it.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's like, even if I want it, I'll put what I know first.
[SPEAKER_02]: And what I know first is this is not suitable.
[SPEAKER_02]: But I want it, doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_02]: You sustain that long enough, you will start seeing the difference between wanting it and me being that wanting.
[SPEAKER_02]: You just... there is wanting, but there is perspective.
[SPEAKER_02]: There is body.
[SPEAKER_02]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: There is the natural fatigue of the body.
[SPEAKER_02]: There are then tendencies of the senses.
[SPEAKER_02]: But by now, I am not automatically identified with them, because I actually sustained and protected them from going into that unwholesome food and areas.
[SPEAKER_02]: They were perpetuating and aggravating this identification and confusion.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's like beginning to see the signs of your mind, means beginning to see this
[SPEAKER_02]: You're beginning to develop this unidentification with your own point of view.
[SPEAKER_02]: You recognize it.
[SPEAKER_02]: It is so.
[SPEAKER_02]: I see it.
[SPEAKER_02]: I see what it leads to.
[SPEAKER_02]: But I still am able to now emphasize the restraint or the perspective.
[SPEAKER_02]: I'm not automatically just merge with it and directed by it.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that, yeah, that's, you know, right view, seeing, yeah, this body has not, not self, that mind has, yeah, self.
[SPEAKER_03]: So you can, by just adopting that view of this, that creature over here, you know, that creature,
[SPEAKER_03]: over there.
[SPEAKER_03]: You're already doing this separation, non-identification at the same time.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's been developed.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, but again, to qualify, because some of you might hear this and then they think they can just jump right into that part of the practice.
[SPEAKER_02]: I'll just keep seeing this is a creature and saying it's not mine.
[SPEAKER_02]: That comes
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, you can do that theoretically.
[SPEAKER_02]: That will basically start to apply and take root correctly, concretely, only if you are and have been restrained beforehand and kept yourself withdrawn from the floods of sensuality and ill-will.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then there is, oh, this is not mine.
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, actually, yeah, look, it's not mine.
[SPEAKER_02]: The dimension of it becomes clearer.
[SPEAKER_02]: You can consider it as, you know... You can consider it, but you have to see it's going to come as a result of the right withdrawal.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: You can't induce the withdrawal through just telling to yourself that this is not mine.
[SPEAKER_02]: It will just result in dismissing the responsibility for the actions that are yours, because you are identified.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, what do I... what's good for me?
[SPEAKER_03]: What should I do?
[SPEAKER_03]: What should I not... shouldn't I do?
[SPEAKER_03]: We're doing that, you know, refraining in the right way.
[SPEAKER_03]: Then, you can get a perspective and regard yourself as another creature.
[SPEAKER_03]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_03]: You know, it's just a very close one.
[SPEAKER_02]: The closest to this point of view, yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: And, and then,
[SPEAKER_03]: Being accomplished in that, in some degree, that will obviously spill out.
[SPEAKER_04]: Well, exactly, because... That's the only way you can actually have sympathy, genuine sympathy, with anybody.
[SPEAKER_03]: This creature over here, that creature over there, are just creature.
[SPEAKER_02]: An example... And the experience of other creatures, agreeable or disagreeable experience of others, can only be experienced on account of patiga of this creature.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, if you're witnessing somebody who is who is unpleasant, that is patīgā felt here.
[SPEAKER_02]: This creature is feeling the discomfort of that person, not me.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, if you're developed in regard to this patīgā here, no amount of discomfort caused by others can cause you pain, because, again, the entry point for it, the patīgā here, is something you're fully developed in regard to.
[SPEAKER_02]: It cannot overwhelm you.
[SPEAKER_02]: It cannot overpower you.
[SPEAKER_02]: You cannot lose perspective on account of it.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, by protecting this creature...
[SPEAKER_02]: You are protected against all creatures.
[SPEAKER_02]: And you're protecting them.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, protecting them.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, you are developing the sympathy, that, you know, or compassion.
[SPEAKER_03]: It will be the result of it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Not of annoyance.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: And then, furthering that, is this, what, mudita, non-contentiousness, as I like to translate it, or blending, like, knowing the benefits for both here, this creature, and that creature over there, you know, blending, like, look.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, imagine now, if we are all here individually,
[SPEAKER_02]: Internally, unable to to to be overwhelmed, resist against, act out of the our, uh, fatigue of our own creatures.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, if you are fully tamed, you know, there's not the slightest traces of resistance towards the creature that you are, not slightest trace of resistance to the creature you are, and same for everybody.
[SPEAKER_02]: Disassembly would be completely
[SPEAKER_02]: Because there is no basis for any discrepancy.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, whatever somebody else do, does in here, in the group, none of the group could take that internally through their own particular they're not developed in regard to.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, there will be no ripples internally, regardless of what...
[SPEAKER_02]: So, that's a perfect harmony, because everybody is incapable of resisting their own... the creature that they are.
[SPEAKER_03]: And we might not be saying much to each other, or like... We might be...
[SPEAKER_02]: I might appreciate you today.
[SPEAKER_02]: Or you might not, but it will still be... Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: But you wouldn't need to be... Well, you can't express this externally.
[SPEAKER_02]: No amount of external expression of...
[SPEAKER_02]: Gratitude and so on means anything to whether the fact that you are still moved by your own resistance in regard to your own creature or not.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, whether you're saying it or not, it's irrelevant.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: You might say it if somebody asks you to answer a question, but you wouldn't say believing that through saying it, you're doing it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, that's just a verb statement.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, yeah, that's wishful thinking.
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, may my cheeks pierce heart.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, see, I always express my wish.
[SPEAKER_02]: Every morning I pray to the shrine and I say, may ill-will not arise in me.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, whether you wish or not, are you doing the work on the level of self-loathing, withdrawing from sensuality, not acting out of ill-will or not?
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, that's... you'll get your answer.
[SPEAKER_02]: It always reminds me that simile of the hen and the chicks.
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, may my chicks pierce out safely from the shell, but she doesn't sit on her eggs.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, they won't.
[SPEAKER_02]: Even if she wishes for the rest of her life, every moment of her life, if she just prays that they pierce out, they won't, because she's not doing the work.
[SPEAKER_02]: And the other type of hen who sits on the eggs, even if she doesn't wish, may they pierce out safely into this world, they will.
[SPEAKER_02]: They will come to
[SPEAKER_01]: So, also, it is said between passing, like, if you practice this rightly, you will see your own sense of self
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, all other others, actual, factual others, will be already on that side of you seeing yourself as other.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, it could be even further others.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, it's just further away, but still, it's that one dimension.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, when that sutra speaks about, you know, one quarter here, there, and so on, it seems to me it's describing a certain kind of totality, because this division between the identification, which is me and others,
[SPEAKER_01]: It's now changed on account of seeing that your sense of self is no longer yours.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's sort of there, and that is already where all others were.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, cultivate metta, in that sense, towards yourself rightly, by disowning your experience, basically, and the whole thing is disowned.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: It was the same principle in regard to satipaṭṭhānas.
[SPEAKER_02]: Or, to the extent necessary, knowing the body is there.
[SPEAKER_02]: The body is the world.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, seeing this creature in its totality, fully developing in regard to its own patiga, is basically the world of others, everything.
[SPEAKER_02]: Everything is within it.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, that direction, this direction, up, down, every way, it's within that creature.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then, that then leads to the complete, the fourth, the upeka.
[SPEAKER_03]: The non-resistance.
[SPEAKER_02]: The non-resistance.
[SPEAKER_02]: The slightest traces of resistance left in regard to anything.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, see, now it's even not anymore on the level of this creature, those creatures, personal, impersonal.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's just resistance and absence of it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Complete purification and removal of the traces.
[SPEAKER_04]: Just need to come back briefly to
[SPEAKER_04]: That point about...
[SPEAKER_04]: I just wanted to maybe emphasize it a little bit more, that... about sympathy or compassion being, like, really the result of first developing non-ill-will, non-resistance, you know, in regard to yourself, your own creature, towards others generally, rather than... in other words, like,
[SPEAKER_04]: You know, you said at one point, you know, you can have the inclination to care for people or, you know, to want to care for the world generally or to be sympathetic with others.
[SPEAKER_04]: But that's... if you haven't developed non-ill-will, that's not actually going to be genuine sympathy.
[SPEAKER_04]: If you don't have understanding of what's genuinely beneficial and unbeneficial and have developed that in regard to yourself, your sympathy will be kind of on the level of, I sympathize
[SPEAKER_04]: With people who are unhappy because of circumstances or something.
[SPEAKER_04]: But you won't really understand.
[SPEAKER_04]: If you don't understand where suffering comes from and have understood that and developed that in yourself, then you can't really be sympathetic on the right level with people who, you know, in... or with anybody or with anything.
[SPEAKER_04]: Because, yeah, your kind of sympathy is already based on a perversion of the idea of
[SPEAKER_04]: So, yeah, I think that's kind of important to note that, like, you can't... you don't... you shouldn't even worry or think about trying to be... have compassion or be sympathetic, really, towards others, unless you've first
[SPEAKER_04]: Basically, you understood the root of suffering.
[SPEAKER_04]: But then you would be automatically... And then you automatically wouldn't need to think about sympathizing with others.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's more like a natural result of that.
[SPEAKER_02]: And if you wanted help, you could get straight to the point.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, you would actually know what... What constitutes help.
[SPEAKER_02]: What constitutes help, what is helpful.
[SPEAKER_04]: And to what extent help is possible and not possible.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.